<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0"
    xmlns:itunes="http://www.itunes.com/dtds/podcast-1.0.dtd">
  <channel>
    <title>African American History: From Emancipation to the Present (2010)</title>
    <itunes:owner>
        <itunes:email>Yale Open Courses</itunes:email>
    </itunes:owner>
    <itunes:author>Professor Jonathan Holloway</itunes:author>
    <description>&lt;p&gt;The purpose of this course is to examine the African American experience in the United States from 1863 to the present (2010). Prominent themes include the end of the Civil War and the beginning of Reconstruction; African Americans’ urbanization experiences; the development of the modern civil rights movement and its aftermath; and the thought and leadership of Booker T. Washington, Ida B. Wells-Barnett, W.E.B. Du Bois, Marcus Garvey, Martin Luther King Jr., and Malcolm X.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    <itunes:image href="https://oyc.yale.edu/sites/default/files/holloway_1_2.jpg"/>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <link>https://oyc.yale.edu/african-american-studies/afam-162</link>
        <item>
      <title> - Dawn of Freedom</title>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Professor Holloway offers an introduction to the course. He explains the organization of the course and summarizes some of the key concepts that will be explored over the course of the semester. Professor Holloway uses the African American experience as a prism to understand American history, because, as he notes, the African American experience speaks to the very heart of what it means to be American. He highlights specific examples of the linkage between freedom, citizenship, and the denial of citizenship, including an ex-slave’s epitaph and Confederate scrip. Finally, Professor Holloway shows how the post-emancipation African American experience is a history of political struggle, social protest, social control, cultural celebration, and a history of powerful relevance today for many of its political and cultural symbols.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <enclosure url="http://openmedia.yale.edu/cgi-bin/open_yale/media_downloader.cgi?file=/courses/spring10/afam162/mp3/afam162_01_011110.mp3"
                 type="audio/mp3" length="-1"/>
      <itunes:duration>3600</itunes:duration>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">Lecture 1</guid>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title> - Dawn of Freedom (continued)</title>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In this lecture, Professor Holloway gives a brief summary of what was happening in the decades leading up to the Civil War, including the Missouri Compromise, the Dred Scott decision, and John Brown’s raid at Harpers Ferry. He discusses the Civil War, focusing specifically on the Emancipation Proclamation and the Conscription Acts of 1863. Professor Holloway spends the duration of the lecture focusing on the labor and racial tensions that led to the New York City draft riots and their aftermath. The crucible of the Civil War, he argues, gives a very clear picture of what it means to be a citizen and what it means to be American. Professor Holloway then gives specific examples of how citizenship was linked to freedom, how freedom was linked to race, and how the tensions between these linkages produced extreme violence.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <enclosure url="http://openmedia.yale.edu/cgi-bin/open_yale/media_downloader.cgi?file=/courses/spring10/afam162/mp3/afam162_02_011310.mp3"
                 type="audio/mp3" length="-1"/>
      <itunes:duration>3600</itunes:duration>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">Lecture 2</guid>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title> - Reconstruction</title>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Between 1865 and 1877, several plans were developed by which the Confederate states could be readmitted to the Union and the residents of the states given full citizenship rights. It was far from clear, however, which plan would do a better job maintaining the social peace and protecting African Americans’ ability to earn a wage, raise a family, own land, and exercise the right to vote. In this lecture, Professor Holloway outlines the contours of the Ten Percent Plan, Presidential Reconstruction, and Radical Reconstruction, and he explains how these plans embraced a variety of approaches to reuniting the disparate states. As Professor Holloway explains, Reconstruction greatly enhanced the rights of African Americans, while also circumscribing their lives by new political, economic, and social initiatives.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <enclosure url="http://openmedia.yale.edu/cgi-bin/open_yale/media_downloader.cgi?file=/courses/spring10/afam162/mp3/afam162_03_011510.mp3"
                 type="audio/mp3" length="-1"/>
      <itunes:duration>3600</itunes:duration>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">Lecture 3</guid>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title> - Reconstruction (continued)</title>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;After the massive cultural shift that the South endured under Reconstruction, white Southerners were determined to fight back. In this lecture, Professor Holloway discusses the complicated meaning of Redemption as white Southerners rose up, reclaimed, and redeemed that which they thought was theirs. During this era, African Americans experienced extreme forms of violence as whites guaranteed the return of power, including the resurgence of the KKK, as well as gerrymandering and poll taxes to ensure the elimination of blacks as a voting class. In the second half of the lecture, Professor Holloway focuses on the ideas of civilization and manliness, lynchings, and anti-lynching campaigns. Fears of rape and ideas of white womanhood frequently served as the justification for the systematic psychological and economic terrorism of African Americans during the “Rise of Redemption.”&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <enclosure url="http://openmedia.yale.edu/cgi-bin/open_yale/media_downloader.cgi?file=/courses/spring10/afam162/mp3/afam162_04_012010.mp3"
                 type="audio/mp3" length="-1"/>
      <itunes:duration>3600</itunes:duration>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">Lecture 4</guid>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title> - Uplift, Accommodation, and Assimilation</title>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In the closing decades of the 1800s, African Americans witnessed the end of Reconstruction, the Redemption of the white South, and increased threats to their political, economic, physical, and psychological well-being. Historians often refer to this era as the “nadir,” the lowest point, in the post-Emancipation black experience. But, as Professor Holloway explains in this lecture, the oppressive realities of black life did not silence the most dedicated black activists. During this time, a new generation of black political and intellectual leaders, including Alexander Crummell, Anna Julia Cooper, and W. E. B. Du Bois, dedicated themselves to “uplifting” blacks politically, economically, and morally. As Professor Holloway reveals, uplift meant different things to different people, acting as both a subversive and conservative ideology.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <enclosure url="http://openmedia.yale.edu/cgi-bin/open_yale/media_downloader.cgi?file=/courses/spring10/afam162/mp3/afam162_05_012510.mp3"
                 type="audio/mp3" length="-1"/>
      <itunes:duration>3600</itunes:duration>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">Lecture 5</guid>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title> - Uplift, Accommodation, and Assimilation (continued)</title>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In this lecture, Professor Holloway explains the two major schools of thought that emerged at the end of the century to solve the problems of black social and economic distress. The accommodationists, like Booker T. Washington, believed that the quickest way to improve the quality of black life was to forge a social peace with powerful whites, temporarily accepting the continued separation of the races and advocating vocational education as a pragmatic way for blacks to improve their lives. Opposed to Washington were people like Anna Julia Cooper and W.E.B. Du Bois who embraced assimilation and saw higher education as the cure-all to racialized problems. Du Bois, in particular, is famous for his assertion that it would be the “Talented Tenth” of the race who would lead blacks to a better life.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <enclosure url="http://openmedia.yale.edu/cgi-bin/open_yale/media_downloader.cgi?file=/courses/spring10/afam162/mp3/afam162_06_012710.mp3"
                 type="audio/mp3" length="-1"/>
      <itunes:duration>3600</itunes:duration>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">Lecture 6</guid>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title> - Migration and Urbanization</title>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In this lecture, Professor Holloway documents the “Great Migration,” beginning in the first decade of the twentieth century and continuing with increasing pace until the mid-1920s. During this time, black Americans relocated from the rural South to the urban North. This general shift in the population marked a moment of self-determination for African Americans, demonstrating that they were prepared to leave behind the lives they had made in the South for better opportunities elsewhere. It is important to see these migrations as a form of social protest against the limited political and economic opportunity in the South, racial violence, and the KKK, which was reborn and flourished in the early 1920s. As Professor Holloway reveals, urban life in the North was frequently cruel and often difficult, but it was also a life forged of free will and absent a regional and cultural history of forced bondage. The remainder of the lecture focuses on how whites’ racial anxieties were manifested in the cultural realm, using D.W. Griffith’s popular film &lt;em&gt;Birth of a Nation.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <enclosure url="http://openmedia.yale.edu/cgi-bin/open_yale/media_downloader.cgi?file=/courses/spring10/afam162/mp3/afam162_07_020110.mp3"
                 type="audio/mp3" length="-1"/>
      <itunes:duration>3600</itunes:duration>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">Lecture 7</guid>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title> - Migration and Urbanization (continued)</title>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In this lecture, Professor Holloway expands our understanding of “The Great Migration” by looking at what happens when African Americans settled in Northern and Midwestern cities. He examines the 1917 East St. Louis race riot, the 1919 Chicago race riot, and the NAACP’s Silent Protest Parade from New York City’s Fifth Avenue to Harlem. The second portion of the lecture is on African American soldiers’ experiences abroad during World War, their rising expectations for citizenship rights when they return, the new militancy that they espoused, and the racial backlash against them by whites. Black soldiers, returning to the U.S. after risking their lives in war, were lynched in uniform. Responding to this backlash, Professor Holloway shows how civil rights activist W.E.B. Du Bois and poet Claude McKay foreshadowed the new political climate in which African Americans would assert their rights.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <enclosure url="http://openmedia.yale.edu/cgi-bin/open_yale/media_downloader.cgi?file=/courses/spring10/afam162/mp3/afam162_08_020310.mp3"
                 type="audio/mp3" length="-1"/>
      <itunes:duration>3600</itunes:duration>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">Lecture 8</guid>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title> - The New Negroes</title>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In this lecture, Professor Holloway discusses the New Negro mentality, a new black consciousness forged out of political and economic frustration and the cultural shocks of the Great Migration. The New Negro ideology was articulated on a wide scale after World War I, when the promises of democracy at home went unfulfilled. Marcus Garvey best articulated this new consciousness through his Universal Negro Improvement Association (UNIA), the first organized grassroots mass protest movement in African American history. Garvey advocated black pride and autonomy, worked to build a great steam line so blacks could partake in nation-building, and helped dispirited blacks dream of an eventual return to Africa. Garvey’s ability to realize his dreams was limited by his own organizational ineptitude and by the federal government’s systematic attempts to infiltrate and then destroy the UNIA. The lecture ends with an examination of Garvey’s relationships to other black leaders, including Father Divine and his Peace Mission Movement.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <enclosure url="http://openmedia.yale.edu/cgi-bin/open_yale/media_downloader.cgi?file=/courses/spring10/afam162/mp3/afam162_09_020810.mp3"
                 type="audio/mp3" length="-1"/>
      <itunes:duration>3600</itunes:duration>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">Lecture 9</guid>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title> - The New Negroes (continued)</title>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The Harlem Renaissance brought together legions of black writers, artists, musicians, and intellectuals who celebrated black culture and romanticized its connections to an African past. In this lecture, Professor Holloway documents some of the expressions of the Harlem Renaissance (also known as the New Negro Renaissance), the political and cultural movement that claimed Harlem as its figurative capital. In fact, thousands of African Americans flocked to Harlem, and it became the center of a rich cultural and political environment–one always fraught with complications, but still understood to represent the best that black America had to offer. As Professor Holloway shows, white enthusiasts of these newly-admired cultural forms visited Harlem to get a taste of black life. Indeed, without the financial support of the white community, whatever cultural efflorescence that did exist in Harlem would have been significantly less grand. Yet the tensions between white patrons and black artists, as well as between black intellectuals and black artists, made the Harlem Renaissance a complex movement.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <enclosure url="http://openmedia.yale.edu/cgi-bin/open_yale/media_downloader.cgi?file=/courses/spring10/afam162/mp3/afam162_10_021010.mp3"
                 type="audio/mp3" length="-1"/>
      <itunes:duration>3600</itunes:duration>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">Lecture 10</guid>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title> - Depression and Double V</title>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The 1930s was a decade filled with economic, legal, political, and social controversy. In this lecture, Professor Holloway looks at the Great Depression and the federal government’s responses to it, including the New Deal’s impact on African Americans, both materially and symbolically. As the federal government openly courted their favor, African Americans organized various political groups to monitor federal activities. In the second portion of the lecture, Professor Holloway examines the achievements of the Black Cabinet, the injustices of the Scottsboro Boys’ case, and the efficacy of the “Don’t Buy Where You Can’t Work” campaigns, led in Washington, D.C., by the New Negro Alliance. As much as the 1930s were about retrenchment for African Americans, they also reflected new political possibilities and new forms of political expression within black America. Thus, as Professor Holloway reveals, the roots of the modern civil rights movement are all part and parcel of New Deal America.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <enclosure url="http://openmedia.yale.edu/cgi-bin/open_yale/media_downloader.cgi?file=/courses/spring10/afam162/mp3/afam162_11_021510.mp3"
                 type="audio/mp3" length="-1"/>
      <itunes:duration>3600</itunes:duration>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">Lecture 11</guid>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title> - Depression and Double V (continued)</title>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In this lecture, Professor Holloway continues discussing African American political possibilities in the second half of the 1930s by examining the new mentality at work in black America. He focuses on the National Negro Congress, the Marian Anderson Easter Sunday Concert, and the March on Washington movement. These examples reveal the diverse strategies and organizing methods employed during this era, as the federal government learned that it could not afford to ignore black leaders the way it had since the founding of the Republic. Professor Holloway also examines the radical possibilities of this decade, as black Communists and Socialists advanced democratic visions for the country. For a brief moment, these ideas appeared to have traction. Yet as the Cold War marched on, charges of communism would decimate some African American civil rights groups.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <enclosure url="http://openmedia.yale.edu/cgi-bin/open_yale/media_downloader.cgi?file=/courses/spring10/afam162/mp3/afam162_12_021710.mp3"
                 type="audio/mp3" length="-1"/>
      <itunes:duration>3600</itunes:duration>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">Lecture 12</guid>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title> - The Road to Brown and Little Rock</title>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In this lecture, Professor Holloway presents an overview of the civil rights events that took place between the end of World War II and &lt;em&gt;Brown v. Board of Education&lt;/em&gt; in 1954. A critical survey of the histories behind such famous events as the desegregation of the Armed Forces, the formation of the Congress on Racial Equality (CORE), the elimination of the all-white primary, and the Supreme Court’s &lt;em&gt;Brown&lt;/em&gt; decision demonstrate how complicated the story of the civil rights movement is. Professor Holloway canvasses events on the high political stage as well as in the legal arena to understand the fundamental shift, taking place in the country on racial issues. An examination of civil rights organizing practices and legal strategies in the 1940s, in particular, helps provide a framework for re-periodizing the movement.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <enclosure url="http://openmedia.yale.edu/cgi-bin/open_yale/media_downloader.cgi?file=/courses/spring10/afam162/mp3/afam162_13_022410.mp3"
                 type="audio/mp3" length="-1"/>
      <itunes:duration>3600</itunes:duration>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">Lecture 13</guid>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title> - From Sit-Ins to Civil Rights</title>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Martin Luther King, Jr. and the civil rights movement have become embodied in each other. But in this lecture, Professor Holloway asks: what of the other activists in the struggle? What of the other organizations involved in the struggle? And what of the history of the struggle before King reluctantly emerged on the scene? By uncovering the histories of the Montgomery bus boycott, the integration of Central High School in Little Rock, the death of Emmett Till, the Greensboro student sit-ins, and the formation of the Southern Christian Leadership Conference and the Student Nonviolent Coordinating Committee, one finds differing responses to violence and multiple approaches to attacking racial bias and discrimination. Professor Holloway also draws attention to the gender dynamics of the civil rights movement by considering the inner-workings of the Women’s Political Council in Montgomery, Alabama, the original motivating force behind the 1955 bus boycott, and the great importance of respectability to the movement. This lecture reveals that there was no single civil rights movement, that there were many activists working in a variety of different ways and with varying degrees of success, and that King was a complicated figure, both inspiring and stifling activism.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <enclosure url="http://openmedia.yale.edu/cgi-bin/open_yale/media_downloader.cgi?file=/courses/spring10/afam162/mp3/afam162_14_030110.mp3"
                 type="audio/mp3" length="-1"/>
      <itunes:duration>3600</itunes:duration>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">Lecture 14</guid>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title> - From Sit-Ins to Civil Rights (continued)</title>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In this lecture, Professor Holloway offers a richer portrait of Martin Luther King, Jr. than his “I Have a Dream Speech” speech provides. Though King’s message and delivery are precious moments in this nation’s history, and excerpts are familiar to virtually all American school children, King’s opinion of society and its remedy have been frozen in time and reduced to a few moments of his famous speech. Professor Holloway frees King from his magnificent yet soothing speech in order to appreciate the real world political and social battles that defined his life and the lives of those who fought beside him in the struggle for freedom and equality. By shedding light on moments that have been dropped out of the “master narrative” of the civil rights movement, Professor Holloway demonstrates that the movement was far from reaching a moment of transcendence at the 1963 March on Washington.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <enclosure url="http://openmedia.yale.edu/cgi-bin/open_yale/media_downloader.cgi?file=/courses/spring10/afam162/mp3/afam162_15_030310.mp3"
                 type="audio/mp3" length="-1"/>
      <itunes:duration>3600</itunes:duration>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">Lecture 15</guid>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title> - From Voting Rights to Watts</title>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In this lecture, Professor Holloway revisits Malcolm X’s life in order to offer a more nuanced interpretation of the black leader than is traditionally taught. Professor Holloway links Malcolm X to a tradition of black intellectuals and political activists like Booker T. Washington, Marcus Garvey, and Robert Williams, and he explores the philosophy of the Nation of Islam (NOI), the organization for which Malcolm X is the national spokesman before his split with Elijah Muhammad in 1964. In the final year of his life, prior to his assassination by NOI members in 1965, Malcolm X makes a religious journey to Mecca, rejects his prior views on race, starts the Organization of Afro-American Unity, and adopts the name El-Hajj Malik El-Shabazz. In the remainder of the lecture, Professor Holloway backtracks to explore some of the other historical events that frame the civil rights movement, including Freedom Summer, the Mississippi Freedom Democratic Party, and the 1964 Civil Rights Act.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <enclosure url="http://openmedia.yale.edu/cgi-bin/open_yale/media_downloader.cgi?file=/courses/spring10/afam162/mp3/afam162_16_032210.mp3"
                 type="audio/mp3" length="-1"/>
      <itunes:duration>3600</itunes:duration>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">Lecture 16</guid>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title> - From Voting Rights to Watts (continued)</title>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In this lecture, Professor Holloway focuses on the events between 1964 and 1966 that contribute to a fundamental shift in the tone and tactics of the civil rights movement. By examining the Mississippi Freedom Democratic Party’s quest to seat alternate delegates at the Democratic National Convention in 1964; “Bloody Sunday” and the 1965 march from Selma to Montgomery; the signing of the 1965 Voting Rights Act; and the riots that summer in Watts, a poor neighborhood in Los Angeles, Professor Holloway reveals that people were struggling with the new tactical change in the movement. The militancy seen in Watts was becoming more recognizable and more frequent, partially due to rhetoric but also do to the increasing U.S. military occupation in Vietnam. Impatience was growing not just in urban or northern areas, but all over the country. In the final portion of the lecture, Professor Holloway offers a preview of the first Black Panther Party, the Lowndes County Freedom Organization, founded in Lowndes County, Mississippi, and the shifting racial philosophy of the Student Non-Violent Coordinating Committee, led by Stokely Carmichael.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <enclosure url="http://openmedia.yale.edu/cgi-bin/open_yale/media_downloader.cgi?file=/courses/spring10/afam162/mp3/afam162_17_032410.mp3"
                 type="audio/mp3" length="-1"/>
      <itunes:duration>3600</itunes:duration>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">Lecture 17</guid>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title> - Black Power</title>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Just as Martin Luther King, Jr. and Malcolm X have been mythologized in American history, organizations and individuals affiliated with the Black Power call have also been romanticized as well as demonized in such a way that the truth behind their image has been lost. In this lecture, Professor Holloway uncovers the history of black radicalism in the sixties, most famously embodied by the Black Panther Party, and reveals how black power encompassed a call for race pride, the development of black-run organizations dedicated to saving black communities, and also a fascination with an image–one conferred upon black radicals by whites as well as consciously cultivated by African Americans. At the same time, this hyper-masculine, cool, soulful, and dangerous aesthetic obscured some of the important work that the black militants tried to accomplish. In the second half of this lecture, Professor Holloway reveals how groups like the Black Panthers created their own community social welfare programming and maintained links between their cause and that of oppressed people around the world.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <enclosure url="http://openmedia.yale.edu/cgi-bin/open_yale/media_downloader.cgi?file=/courses/spring10/afam162/mp3/afam162_18_032910.mp3"
                 type="audio/mp3" length="-1"/>
      <itunes:duration>3600</itunes:duration>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">Lecture 18</guid>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title> - Black Power (continued)</title>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;As the movement moved out of the South and away from a largely Christian orientation, it became clear that people were prepared to enlarge the struggle so that it became linked to international issues including the war in Vietnam, the spread of capitalism, and the exploitation of developing countries. Yet for every moment of great promise, there was a moment of great confusion and despair. In this lecture, Professor Holloway traces the competing lines of activism, change, struggle, frustration, and political brinksmanship that occurred in the late sixties. He focuses on SNCC’s trajectory, Martin Luther King’s poverty campaign in Chicago, his views on Vietnam, the riots that followed his 1968 assassination, and the Poor People’s Campaign. The remainder of the lecture focuses on the national and international events of 1968 that contributed to this feeling of unrest sweeping the country. As the movement grew beyond its traditional boundaries, the moral and psychological hold it had on America began to lose its strength. As Professor Holloway explains, by the end of the 1960s, it seemed that Americans cared little for the larger and more complicated truths pointed to by black radicals’ political, social, economic, and cultural critique.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <enclosure url="http://openmedia.yale.edu/cgi-bin/open_yale/media_downloader.cgi?file=/courses/spring10/afam162/mp3/afam162_19_033110.mp3"
                 type="audio/mp3" length="-1"/>
      <itunes:duration>3600</itunes:duration>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">Lecture 19</guid>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title> - The Politics of Gender and Culture</title>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The early 1970s marked a moment of social confusion, violence, and cultural excitement carried over from the late 1960s. In this lecture, Professor Holloway canvasses some of the political turmoil of this era and the ways that it was reflected in popular culture. By examining musical achievements like Marvin Gaye’s album, &lt;em&gt;What’s Going On?&lt;/em&gt;, and some of Stevie Wonder’s songs recorded around this time, it becomes clear that black cultural producers were wrestling with Vietnam, economic despair, ecological despair, poverty, and urban decay. Yet the early 1970s was also a moment of black cultural celebration, and Professor Holloway explores the complicated messages about black sexuality in general, and black masculinity and the role of black women in specific, depicted in blaxploitation films like &lt;em&gt;Shaft&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Sweet Sweetback’s Badasssss Song&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Super Fly&lt;/em&gt;, and &lt;em&gt;Foxy Brown&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <enclosure url="http://openmedia.yale.edu/cgi-bin/open_yale/media_downloader.cgi?file=/courses/spring10/afam162/mp3/afam162_20_040510.mp3"
                 type="audio/mp3" length="-1"/>
      <itunes:duration>3600</itunes:duration>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">Lecture 20</guid>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title> - The Politics of Gender and Culture (continued)</title>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;With Martin Luther King’s assassination, the collapse of SNCC, and the self-destruction of the Black Panthers, one would think that all promise had faded in regards to the possibility of black political and social advancement. But in this lecture, Professor Holloway examines moments of hope for black political organization, including Carl Stokes’s 1967 mayoral victory in Cleveland, the formation of the Congressional Black Caucus in 1969, and the 1972 National Black Political Convention in Gary, Indiana. Yet for all of the coalition building taking place, deeper problems revolved around gender. In this lecture, Professor Holloway focuses specifically on the difficulties that black women encountered as they confronted a racist and sexist political system, exemplified by Daniel Patrick Moynihan’s concern over women-headed households in black America. When Shirley Chisholm declared her candidacy for the presidency, and when women on the ground, like Johnnie Tillman, fought for welfare rights or tried to join the modern feminist movement, they faced their “double jeopardy,” that is a second-class status rooted in both racial and gender oppression. Although the early 1970s certainly was not the first time black women began to speak up about their oppression, Professor Holloway reveals that they finally began to be heard, and they formed groups, like the National Black Feminist Organization and the Combahee River Collective, to try to change the national conversation.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <enclosure url="http://openmedia.yale.edu/cgi-bin/open_yale/media_downloader.cgi?file=/courses/spring10/afam162/mp3/afam162_21_040710.mp3"
                 type="audio/mp3" length="-1"/>
      <itunes:duration>3600</itunes:duration>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">Lecture 21</guid>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title> - Public Policy and Presidential Politics</title>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In this lecture, Professor Holloway gives a political biography of Jesse Jackson as a way to help understand the shifting cultural politics of the 1960s, the rise of a different array of politics in the 1970s, and the high politics of the 1980s. Professor Holloway traces Jackson’s ascension into Martin Luther King’s inner-circle, his work in Chicago with Operation Breadbasket and then later with Operation PUSH, his reaction to King’s assassination, his national economic boycotts, and his 1984 and 1988 presidential campaigns. In the second half of the lecture, Professor Holloway turns to the national stage, surveying the political and social milieu around President Nixon, Ford, Carter, and Reagan’s administrations, focusing specifically on the latter two. While Jimmy Carter diversified the executive branch of the federal government through White House appointments, Ronald Reagan had a more covert approach to racial politics. By claiming that the federal government was the real problem, and calling for a return to states’ rights, Reagan implicitly supported the centralizing power of racists like Bull Connor and organizations like the KKK. Thus, Professor Holloway explains, as public race baiting fell out of favor, conservatives like Reagan adopted a way of talking about race without ever mentioning it.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <enclosure url="http://openmedia.yale.edu/cgi-bin/open_yale/media_downloader.cgi?file=/courses/spring10/afam162/mp3/afam162_22_041210.mp3"
                 type="audio/mp3" length="-1"/>
      <itunes:duration>3600</itunes:duration>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">Lecture 22</guid>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title> - Public Policy and Presidential Politics (continued)</title>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In this lecture, Professor Holloway discusses the connections between media and high politics during the late 1980s and 1990s and reveals the ways that race was replaced by a series of keywords–such as crime, drugs, and welfare–that acted as racial signifiers in our national discourse. An examination of the political rhetoric from the George H.W. Bush/Michael Dukakis campaign, including the infamous Willie Horton advertisement, as well as racially-infused persons and incidents such as Bernhard Goetz, the “Subway Vigilante;” Charles Stuart; the Central Park jogger case; Senator Jesse Helms’s “Angry Hands” advertisement; the murder of Latasha Harlins by Soon Ja Du, a Korean shopkeeper; the Rodney King beating; and the riots and rebellion in South Central, Los Angeles following the acquittal of the white policemen who beat him all reveal the special coding that linked people’s awareness of race and crime and the ways that the media reinforced the stereotype that crime was the special province of the black male. In the remainder of the lecture, Professor Holloway discusses the Clarence Thomas/Anita Hill controversy, essentially a manifestation of the three-ring circus that was racial politics in the 1990s.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <enclosure url="http://openmedia.yale.edu/cgi-bin/open_yale/media_downloader.cgi?file=/courses/spring10/afam162/mp3/afam162_23_041410.mp3"
                 type="audio/mp3" length="-1"/>
      <itunes:duration>3600</itunes:duration>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">Lecture 23</guid>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title> - Who Speaks for the Race?</title>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In this lecture, Professor Holloway discusses how race influenced public policy by examining some of the key cultural symbols of the past few decades, all in an effort to answer the question: how is race used in our society? Professor Holloway discusses Bill Clinton’s policies in particular, honing in on his ability to connect with the African American community, the controversy surrounding Lani Guinier’s cabinet appointment, and his National Dialogue on Race. He then turns to California to examine the passage of Propositions 187 and 209, which begin to call into question common notions about civil rights legislation and affirmative action in our nation. In the remainder of the lecture, Professor Holloway talks about four landmark court cases–&lt;em&gt;Shaw v. Reno&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Adarand v. Pena&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Hopwood v. Texas&lt;/em&gt;, and &lt;em&gt;Grutter v. Bollinger&lt;/em&gt;–to shed light on the way race began to operate in a legal setting, as well as the general dumbing down of discourse in politics and media about race, in the post-civil rights era.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <enclosure url="http://openmedia.yale.edu/cgi-bin/open_yale/media_downloader.cgi?file=/courses/spring10/afam162/mp3/afam162_24_041910.mp3"
                 type="audio/mp3" length="-1"/>
      <itunes:duration>3600</itunes:duration>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">Lecture 24</guid>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title> - Who Speaks for the Race? (continued)</title>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In this final lecture, Professor Holloway offers a survey of some of the main themes and ideas of the course, including citizenship, uplift and respectability, political radicalism, cultural politics, and racial symbolism. The final two questions he grapples with are 1) what does it mean to be “post-racial” and 2) how is race used in our society? In order to propose answers to these questions, Professor Holloway examines Barack Obama’s election; his 2008 inauguration; and his speech, “A More Perfect Union,” given during the campaign. He also provides some examples of the ways raced is used in the American landscape to distract attention from class and gender; to sell products, including Uncle Ben’s rice and Aunt Jemima’s pancakes; to suggest a progressive commitment to equality; to draw in tourist money; and to heighten emotions, as illustrated by some of the ways that New Orleans’ residents were depicted during Hurricane Katrina. In the end, Professor Holloway argues that race is used in ways that are, whether intentionally or by accident, at best simplistic and at worst destructive, often because we are unwilling to talk or think about these issues in complicated ways. He then leaves the students with one final question: how will you use race?&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <enclosure url="http://openmedia.yale.edu/cgi-bin/open_yale/media_downloader.cgi?file=/courses/spring10/afam162/mp3/afam162_25_042110.mp3"
                 type="audio/mp3" length="-1"/>
      <itunes:duration>3600</itunes:duration>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">Lecture 25</guid>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>